hey guys welcome to concept and coding
this is Shan and today in the spring
boot video we are going to cover the
custom interceptors right very very
important topic because in future
whatever the topics we are going to
cover caching logging authentication we
might have to write our own custom
interceptors so before we touch those
topics this has to be pretty clear so
what is Interceptor actually
uh so I would say in a very simple words
it's a
mediator which get invoked before or
after your actual
code right so this is what we can say as
an
Interceptor so this is the two
prerequisite video I would like to
suggest and the links I will give you in
the description section that this is the
Java ins this Java playlist you will get
this annotation video in depth and in
the spring boot playlist itself I hope
that if you are watching this
Interceptor video uh you are following
the sequence and aop you have already
covered okay with that being said let's
start with the custom
interceptors so now the first is we have
to write a custom Interceptor for
request before even reaching to a
specific controller class right so now
let's say that take this example very
very simple example I have taken a user
controller I have written One controller
rest controller user
controller it has one method which I
have put get mapping annotation and the
path I have given is get
user but I want some custom Interceptor
before even my controller get
involed now if you remember the very
very first video of the spring boot
playlist intro introduction there I
showed you this diagram right so when
the request actually comes right first
it goes to uh the sulet container right
where our application is deployed then
we have something called dispatcher
sulet so dispatcher suet is one which is
responsible right okay the with the
request which is coming
which controller it should assign to so
it will choose the controller
also okay so now we want a custom
Interceptor before reaching to our
particular controller so means somewhere
dispatcher ofet and
this uh invoking the controller method
we our code of custom Interceptor should
get
involed okay so let's see that how can
be
done so let's say that this is
one user controller I have created very
very basic only has one get method get
user and
uh this is the custom Interceptor I have
created so I have created a public class
my custom Interceptor and I have
annotated with at the component means
spring will uh take care of its uh Bean
creation Now here if you see I have
implement it with the Handler
Interceptor so when you implement it
with the Handler Interceptor you have to
provide an implementation for this three
methods preh handle po handle and after
completion okay so preh handle is like
before even your user control method get
invoked this will get
executed after that your actual code
will get executed means your user
controller will get
invoked and once your actual code get
invoked then post handle will get
executed and after that after completion
will get
executed okay so this is the three
methods which is uh the meaning so you
can ask me right herey sh what is the
difference between post handle and after
completion both is getting executed
after my controller I will tell you but
for
now just uh consider this one if we have
implements the Handler Interceptor we
have to provide an implementation of
this three depending upon our needs like
how we want it what we wanted to do in
this okay
now we have to register
this Interceptor like for which API it
has to invoke so how to do that in our
configuration class app config we have
to implement web MVC
configurer inside that we have to
override this method add
Interceptor and inside this method we
have to do a registry so this is the
parameter it accept registry inside this
we have to add our Interceptor hey this
is my custom Interceptor so here if you
see that I have already done at theate
component right so means Bean is already
created that's why I'm just doing at the
rate auto here if if I am not writing it
at the rate component you know what has
to be done at theate Bean here and
creating a new object here okay so
currently I'm doing at theate Auto
because atate component is there so Bean
would be created and that would get Auto
here
so now coming back again to this method
first in the registry we have to add the
interceptors and we have to provide what
is the custom Interceptor we have to
invoke then this two is like first at
path pattern for what all urls we have
to invoke this custom Interceptor so
it's a pattern so it's a comma separated
list right so what I have given is/ API
SL estess
any like/ API SL get user any
API right sis can be replaced with
anything it will get this custom
Interceptor will get
invol now here is one more uh field is
exclude path P patterns so if there are
certain path which you have to exclude
out of this you can specifically mention
this and it can get exclusion
uh so here I mentioned / API / update
user so that would now be excluded and
also delete user also will get excluded
okay for rest
other this Interceptor will get
applied okay so the changes are clear
right we have to first provide
our custom Interceptor where we will
override this uh methods by implementing
the Handler interceptor and we will
provide like what exactly we
wanted okay and then we have to
configure our custom Interceptor like
this so this is for like when before
even our controller get invoked now here
if you
see if I am opening here dispatcher ofet
so here if you see that it is inside
your spring web MVC right and and it is
the dispatcher subet do class we are
inside a dispatcher sulet docl class so
in this one if you see um do
dispatch okay so this is actually
dispatch so here it will do is first
apply the preh handle so when it say
that apply the preh handle means it
first it
will based on this it will invoke this
preh handle
after that it will call ha. handle so
this is the place where actual your
controller will get invoked this is the
place your actual controller will get
invoked so now
means your controller get invoked now
your code will get executed now see
difference between post handle and after
completion so now your controller get
executed after it's completed it is
running the post handle right okay so it
makes sense post post so after your
controller this code will get
executed now what about this
after so this after is like say that
whether it's a success or even if there
is
exception after completion will run so
if there any exception your post will
not get executed but after will be so I
think it's similarly like finally in
Java right so no matter even if there is
an
ception after completion will run so
this is Success so whenever so preh
handle run after preh
handle uh your controller then post and
after that uh this success here inside
it is also running
after okay so during success also it
will run and if there is any exception
also it will run after okay so I hope
the difference is clear between post
handle and after completion
so now here if you see if I run this get
user if I hit this get user
API so I have added in the path param /
API SL so anything so it this custom
interception should invoke and it is
also not excluded so first it goes
inside preh
handle then it invoke my controller so
controller is doing
something okay then after that it goes
out post handle and after that
completion even even though it's a
success okay so this is how you do when
you have to intercept the request before
reaching to a specific controller
class okay it it would be helpful in so
many use cases authentication
authorization we'll see that later part
but this should be clear like how to
intercept the calls
before call reach to the control
now the second part
is I want to have a custom Interceptor
for request after reaching to a specific
controller class so now the uh my
controller has been invoked and now it
is invoking particular methods or
something now I want my custom
Interceptor so now we'll see that how to
do that so I will break it down into two
step the step one is creation of custom
annotation
okay so how do you create a first custom
annotation we can create custom
annotation using the keyword at theate
interface
okay so this is an
example where if you see I am
creating my custom annotation so I am
using keyword at theate interface and I
can give whatever name I like for my
annotation I have given the name my
custom annotation okay so now this
annotation I can
use like this like you are using like
atate override at theate something like
rest controller request controller at
theate get mapping similarly now this is
my I have created annotation so I'm
using at theate my custom
annotation okay so currently what it
will do nothing I have just just created
an annotation we will see how to make
use of this annotation but this is one
way we can create our
annotation now very very two important
meta annotation property which we have
to understand right if you go through
this one right you will find totally
in-depth one but here I'm just setting
up the context uh which is very very
important to understand this so this two
meta annotation has to be clear very
well one is at the rate target So Meta
means annotation which are applied over
an
annotation okay so don't worry we will
I'll will tell you how so here at the
Target meta annotation means this meta
annotation
tells where we can apply the particular
annotation right on a method or a class
class or Constructor Etc let's see this
example so I am creating my custom
annotation using a keyword add the rate
interface I am creating my custom
annotation whatever I like now this
annotation I will I should apply it over
method over class over Constructor what
all so using at theate Target meta
annotation I can specify this so here at
the Target I said that element type do
method so means over a method only you
can use this
annotation if you have more than one
places you want to use it you can tell
it like this like an
array element type. Constructor you can
use this annotation my custom annotation
which I have created you can use it over
Constructor over method over par uh
parameters or over fields
also right so there are many ways we can
uh tell that hey yes this annotation you
can use at all this places so this is
the purpose of Target meta annotation
right and I and I think you already got
it why it's called meta annotation means
it is used over an annotation so this is
one of my annotation my custom
annotation so this at theate Target is
you used over a
annotation and another is at theate
retention this meta annotation tells how
the particular annotation will be stored
in
Java so these are the three values one
is retention policy. Source annotation
will be discarded by compiler itself and
it's not even recorded in do class
file right so here if you see this
example I have created an annotation at
theate interface my custom annotation
Target I have given that okay used it
over a method but what is the retention
I have given retention policy.
Source okay so this annotation I'm using
in
a I have created a class user and I have
a method update user over that I am
using it okay so it's valid but when I
am converting I'm doing let's say Java C
now this Java class now converting it to
a bite clod let's say Do class file now
in the dot class file since I am using
Source it will not this annotation will
not get converted or not carry forward
in the dot class file so here if you see
there is no
annotation and if you see at the rate
override annotation right actually it is
source so it is just for the readability
of the
engineers but it do not add any value it
even not even converted to our bite
code okay so annotation will be
discarded by compiler itself and it's
not even recorded in dot class
file there is another retention policies
is do class annotation will be recorded
in do class file but ignored by jvm
during runtime so if you
use do
class then here during this do class
file you might see at theate my
custom
annotation but will it add any value
nothing right because jvm during runtime
will not even considered it and it
totally
ignore right so you can say that it's uh
in the bite code even though it's added
but jvm will not even consider it and
there is something called dot runtime
annotation will be recorded in do class
file and also available during the run
time so so now here for this one only we
can write some custom logic that hey
during your code is running during run
time you can fetch The annotation and do
something based on that okay so here if
you see an example I have creating my
annotation my custom annotation uses the
keyword at theate
interface Target is Method and retention
is
runtime and I'm using this annotation
over this method which which is inside a
user class now I converted it to a do
class file here if you see now here if
you see that it's get inside a do class
file and even during the run time also I
can even do reflection and read hey this
method has any annotation if yes do this
something we'll see that but this three
are the retention
policies so whenever we are creating our
custom annotation right we have to
provide what is the Target and what is
the
retention so this two like we have to
provide now one more very very important
part when we will write our interceptors
right we have to uh you can say that add
some information for a particular method
right so how to in The annotation my
custom annotation how I can send certain
information so there are Fields also so
we can create a custom annotation with
method which is more like a field and
inside this field we can add
value so here this methods which we are
going to write has no parameter no body
first second thing is return type is
very very restricted to primitive in in
Boolean double so there are total eight
uh primitive types so it is limited to
primitive types you can use a string you
can use enum you can use like Class Type
class whether it should be a string dot
class whatever do class right but should
be dot
class right annotations on array of
above you can say string array int array
Boolean array that also can be
used right uh why why there is a
restriction if if something is going in
your in your mind like hey because see
annotations are very lightweight right
we have to keep it very very restricted
because we don't want to expand its uh
use cases and all so that's why this
only return types are allowed and how to
do that I am writing my own custom
annotation my custom annotation with at
theate interface
keyword I have used at theate Target at
theate retention now here if you see I
want one value let's
say key so here if you see that this
method doesn't have any return type and
uh not any parameter and return type is
a string which is allowed
one right and you can provide a default
uh value for this is like like default
default key name now in this class over
this method when I using this annotation
I can pass certain information like this
for this
key value is user key for this method
user key now wherever my Interceptor
will catch it up it can get this value
also from this annotation we will see
tell you how but for now you can say
that when you write a custom
annotation we can pass certain value
like this and when we write our own
Interceptor right during caching dur
during logging this feature going to
help us a lot because we always have to
pass certain information during
interceptors so this is one example I
showed you like with more Fields like I
am writing my custom annotation at the
interface this now I have just for uh
demoing purpose I have written one
method like int key I I don't call it a
method I will call it a field mostly uh
it's a field only generally but this is
the way of representing it inside this
one so int key no parameter return type
is in a string return type is a string
default value you can give anything here
I have given zero Class Type key so this
is the return type default I have
written a string do
class enum key so you can create any
enum so default value is this and return
type is enum
only string array key so you can return
string array default value you can
return any array of the string similarly
like this and in the class when you're
using this you can use my custom
annotation which you have created now
you can pass certain value int key I am
passing 10 a string key a string right
so I'm passing some
user Class Type key I am passing user do
class enum key I am passing some another
Ina so you got it right we can pass
certain values in this annotation so you
can say that these are mostly fields and
we are just filling the values of these
fields and you can provide a default
method like here inside that
itself so at this point of time you
should be clear that how to create a
custom
annotation now you can write your custom
annotation like at theate I can even
create at theate Shan so at this point
we should be clear like how to create
now the second part is creating our
custom
interceptors so now here if you see what
I am doing
here I am creating a user controller
class very very simple class I having
one method get user which is with this
uh path get mapping this is the path and
this is invoking this
user this is is invoking this user class
okay uh annotated with adorate component
beans beans is created by
Spring it has one method called get user
now here if you see that get user I have
annotated with my at theate custom
annotation so this is the custom
annotation I have created now we already
know how to create right and only one
name a string default value is uh empty
so name I can provide user
okay so this is the custom annotation I
have given over the get
user now I want to write my
Interceptor okay if you have seen the
aop video you can easily get it how to
write an Interceptor now I am writing I
am creating a class my custom
Interceptor at theate component tells
that bean should be created by Spring
add theate expect means that this class
will will be considered as an
Interceptor where we'll have a point cut
and
advice okay so now I am writing one
method if if you get a doubt what is
point cut what advice I would say stop
here itself please check out the aop
video and then come back uh otherwise it
will create you the confusion because we
have already discussed the point cut and
advice in depth in
aop so now here if you see
that this
method I am providing one point cut at
the rate
annotation so what atate annotation you
remember you can you
recall it will look for this annotation
which we have provided so com concept
encoding do learning spring boot. custom
Interceptor so this is the path where I
have created this my custom
annotation right so this is the
path for this my custom annotation this
one this one my custom annotation so at
theate annotation
means hey run this advice run this
advice or this
method when whenever you see this
annotation my custom
annotation okay so now here if you see
from here this class user controller I
am controlling I I am calling
this this class user class this method
from user controller I am calling user
class and now this method has annotation
at the rate my custom annotation so what
it will do is it will intercept it and
how intercept will work in the aop I
have already showed you that what how
internally the proxy get involved and
what would
happen so but because of this point card
we can tell that okay listen to this
annotation and once you find this
annotation okay like when a particular
method is invoked and that method is
annotated with that annotation is
specific annotation I have to run this
advice so here if you see that it is
like at theate around means before then
your code and then after so here do
something something before actual method
now see this what I'm doing
here now I have a joint point right from
this joint point I can take out a
method okay this
method right all the metadata
information about this method I can get
what is the return type what is the
parameter is this method has any
annotation all this thing I can do so
now that's the same thing I'm doing hey
this method is annotation present this
my custom annotation if this is present
true then what I doing is from this
method I am taking out this annotation
details so now I am getting this
annotation
detail and see that from this annotation
I can read out this dot
name okay it will print
user okay and after that I have done
some pre-work I just did print in and
after that it called proceed and you
know that when it call proceed what it
happen our actual method will get invoke
this get the user detail and after once
it done it will do something after
actual method so now if you run this
what would happen is it will print do
something before actual method so this
got printed after that
uh when it try to invoke this right when
it try to invoke this method get used us
okay so because of this point cut it
goes here it print
this and here if you see that yes this
method is annotated with my custom
annotation so it will uh annotation
present true it will get The annotation
and it will name from annotation it will
print
user and then ultimately it will call
the method get the user
details and after that do something
after actual
method so we have created our one
Interceptor okay so both the
interceptors I have tell uh told you if
we want to have a Interceptor before
even the controller how we can do that
right and if we want after the
controller like any particular method or
annotation right we have to Pro written
an interception how how we can do
that okay so practice this out a lot
because in future videos we might have
to write few interceptors uh because
that's the that's very much required for
logging for caching for authentication
authorization everything okay guys any
doubts feel free to uh comment uh we
will discuss further thank you bye